<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Posts on walther chen </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/post/index.xml/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Walther Chen</author>
    
    <updated>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 14:04:09 EDT</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title> New Journey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/NewJourney/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 14:04:09 EDT</pubDate>
      <author>Walther Chen</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/NewJourney/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting a new episode in my life! About one month ago, I committed myself
to learning programming and getting a job as a software developer. For at least
the next five years, I want to learn some new skills and explore a new
industry. After that, I&amp;rsquo;ll reassess and see where I want to go next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Learning Programming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned Python through Think Python by Allen Downey, which I think
is an excellent book. I appreciated the thoughtful exercises, and the focus on
teaching only what&amp;rsquo;s useful in the moment while building towards a bigger
project. I find that too much information without implementation results in
shallow learning. Perhaps for other learners, there&amp;rsquo;s a different sweet spot,
but for me Think Python worked great. I&amp;rsquo;m even planning on working through his
book Think Complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some Python basics under my belt, I&amp;rsquo;m investigating some other projects.
The way my brain works, the computational aspect of CS doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem daunting,
but the organizational part does. For example, data structures in a void make sense, but
what&amp;rsquo;s the best way to organize them to do something useful? I guess this is
the software engineering side, and it looks quite open-ended and complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current plans for Python projects are basic inventory management from CLI
and to investigate Flask. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve realized that I&amp;rsquo;m not very results
driven, I&amp;rsquo;m more of a process person. Of course, getting something to work is
satisfying, but I feel uncomfortable with magic and frameworks at the moment
because I don&amp;rsquo;t understand what&amp;rsquo;s going on. So as I continue to explore, those
projects may never get finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the theme of less magic, I&amp;rsquo;ve also been investigating Golang. I&amp;rsquo;ve finally
got it set up, and done some tutorials. I like the simplicity of the language,
and I want to use it to build a simple webserver first. Perhaps to serve sgf
files (Go game records).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a ton of other stuff I also find interesting: SICP,
Haskell, algorithms, data mining and analyis, numerical computing and
modelling. I&amp;rsquo;m all too capable of running off in many different directions. So
I&amp;rsquo;m going to shelve those for now and concentrate on Python and Golang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Finding a Job&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been networking with Williams alumni and they&amp;rsquo;ve been very kind and
helpful. I may have an internship set up for the near future, and I&amp;rsquo;ll also be
looking for other opportunities through more networking. I&amp;rsquo;ve found that my
default of responding to Craigslist ads has not worked especially well, maybe
because of my unconventional background. Although, I&amp;rsquo;m also planning on sending
some cold emails.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>