<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Posts on walther chen </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://waltherchen.com/post/index.xml/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Walther Chen</author>
    
    <updated>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 22:32:18 EST</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Utilities</title>
      <link>http://waltherchen.com/post/utilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 22:32:18 EST</pubDate>
      <author>Walther Chen</author>
      <guid>http://waltherchen.com/post/utilities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exciting! I wrote my first program that&amp;rsquo;s for &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; work! It&amp;rsquo;s a small script to upload files to an ftp server that hosts the MGA ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s kind of funny, it seems like such a simple program when I look at it now. But maybe one month ago, it might have felt very complicated in Haskell. I think that&amp;rsquo;s because it helped this time around to know more about monads and &amp;gt;== and liftM. The steps of the script are not hard, nor was calling the libraries (for ftp, directories, etc.). But understanding what Haskell was actually doing (I think that this would be called semantics?) finally happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a cool little program that saved me the huge annoyance of using a GUI ftp client, while also giving me some fun hands-on coding and digging in libraries, combined with furthering my understanding of Haskell abstractions like monads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, I also just realized that I can easily extend this utility for helping me convert file formats. I currently write in Markdown and convert to html using pandoc (which is written in Haskell!). I had thought that it was a pity that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t call the pandoc executable from inside the script, like I might have done with a bash script&amp;hellip;. But I can integrate the pandoc library into my program! Even more saved keystrokes coming my way! I may even be able to use this script to apply html headers/templates so that it will be easier to add css and javascript to the basic site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, eventually the full site will be database driven (Flask, or maybe even Scotty if there&amp;rsquo;s enough documentation and I have enough guts). But for now, it&amp;rsquo;s fun working on this utility. Following close behind is another CLI utility to generate AGA ratings submission forms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End of Fall</title>
      <link>http://waltherchen.com/post/end_of_fall/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 11:27:49 EST</pubDate>
      <author>Walther Chen</author>
      <guid>http://waltherchen.com/post/end_of_fall/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the end of the fall (and almost the end of the year) and I&amp;rsquo;m still looking. I&amp;rsquo;m actually fairly optimistic, though. I hope to have some nice projects up in time for the new year, I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ll have some good chances then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been growing my skills a lot, it just takes a lot of time. At least for me, it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to learn by just blasting away at a complex project for a couple of weeks. I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing a lot of smaller bits of code, especially Project Euler, while also investigating some larger scale stuff. I&amp;rsquo;m going to write a program to help me manage the MGA ladder, because that&amp;rsquo;s a pretty big pain point (I hate repetitive data entry tasks!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think in terms of learning, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten to a point where books will actually be useful to me now. I just had to do a lot of coding in whatever my way my brain wanted to, now I have a jumping off point for understanding more interesting stuff. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to go through LYAH again, and I&amp;rsquo;ve ordered the data processing cookbook by Shuklan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to use books before, but they felt too &amp;ldquo;boring,&amp;rdquo; which I guess was my brain&amp;rsquo;s code that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t internalize the information in a useful way. I&amp;rsquo;ve read some stuff that said that writing code is most important for beginners (even if it&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;good code&amp;rdquo;), and then reading more code is more important later. I think I was prematurely optimizing a bit, thinking about how to make my code &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; and thinking about clean code. Even in Haskell, I can do quite a bit without understanding all the higher level concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Social Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also started going through algorithms and data structure with a friend from the Go club. I think that it&amp;rsquo;s going to be super helpful. I forget if I mentioned it in a previous post, but I&amp;rsquo;m realizing that I&amp;rsquo;m a very social learner. While I do like to read, most of the integration comes from talking with others. And not just listening, it has to be interactive. I think that&amp;rsquo;s why it felt easy to learn Go and martial arts: lots of social feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also noticed that online classes don&amp;rsquo;t really do it for me. It&amp;rsquo;s very difficult for me to sit passively through a lecture now. So, I won&amp;rsquo;t be doing a lot of online courses on my own, although I&amp;rsquo;ll probably pick up bits and pieces here and there, and I might go through exercises with a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I&amp;rsquo;m going to apply this newfound knowledge! Less &amp;ldquo;trying to figure things out on my own,&amp;rdquo; more looking for like-minded people for all the things I want to learn: yoga, martial arts, Go, programming, languages. (I think that at this point in my life, I&amp;rsquo;m also just less embarassed about what I don&amp;rsquo;t know or can&amp;rsquo;t do).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigation, Haskell and Rust and Job Search</title>
      <link>http://waltherchen.com/post/investigation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 13:35:22 EDT</pubDate>
      <author>Walther Chen</author>
      <guid>http://waltherchen.com/post/investigation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Since my last post, I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing a lot of investigating. I could have jumped even
further down the Python rabbit hole by immediately trying to start on projects. I think
two things stopped me: one, that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a pressing need that I could address with
a project, and two, that my brain was telling me it wanted to explore more what
programming could mean. The result was a foray into Haskell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Haskell&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haskell is described as a lazy, functional language that has a very strong notion of
purity. Great explanations of the language can be found at haskell.org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had messed around with Learn You a Haskell, a great introductory book, but had not
really gotten a grasp on the language. I decided to work through CIS194, a class on
Haskell taught by Brent Yorgey at UPenn, with all materials online! The exercises ended
up being at a great level for me (similar to Think Python). I&amp;rsquo;ve currently worked through
the midway point, right before things get abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that, coming from Python, my greatest delights were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exteremely clean syntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Algebraic Data Types!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maps, filters and folds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found that for me, the syntax makes it really easy to see the structure of the
program. Visual noise takes away from shape, and I&amp;rsquo;m extremely shape-oriented (as I know
from playing Go).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Algebraic Data Types (ADT) were a revelation in terms of rethinking how to organize
programs. For me, they make a lot more sense than what I know about classes and OO
programming. ADTs in Haskell are strict but extremely expressive, and can tell you so
much about the shape of a program up-front without delving into &amp;ldquo;details&amp;rdquo; of execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, to operate in the real world, there needs to be a certain amount of sacrifice
of purity. In Haskell, this often has to do with I/O. I haven&amp;rsquo;t gotten to really grapple
with this part yet, but I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to it as I continue to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Rust&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another language I looked at recently was Rust, which is a new language often compared to
Golang. I&amp;rsquo;m glad I branched out to Haskell, because I learned some things I really
enjoyed in programming (like ADT), and those things really popped out when looking at
Rust. Rust seems to be another imperative programming language in the vein of Python or
C++, but what struck me was that it had its own implementation of ADT! I wrote some toy
programs in Rust, thinking that perhaps the combination of imperative with functional
would fit my mindset really well and make programming easy. But Rust has another trick up
its sleeve: memory-safe programming, which is actually the language&amp;rsquo;s main calling card.
I only know a little, but it looks like Rust places responsibility for keeping track of
when and where memory is allocated to variables, while also creating a framework so that
the compiler can help you keep track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about memory, as well as pointers and mutability explicitly in programs, is
pretty complicated above just making my program run. Python basically took care of it all
for me, with some cost in terms of performance, structure, and safety. Haskell takes care
of those things to, but in part by limiting the programming paradigm. The more technical,
close-to-the-metal stuff hurts my head a bit, and was definitely one of the reasons I
found programming hard in high school and college. (glad I was reintroduced through
Python!). But I&amp;rsquo;m glad to know what&amp;rsquo;s possible in a programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Investigations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to keep investigating both Rust and Haskell. I guess it&amp;rsquo;ll be a little bit of
juggling as I also want to learn Python. But it does seem to me that picking up a bit of
syntax or learning a new language is not too hard for very basic competency (especially C
related languages like Rust or Python). I&amp;rsquo;ve done it a few times now, with these
languages and also Java and Turbo Pascal in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real challenge for me is not being fluent in the &amp;ldquo;syntax&amp;rdquo; of the language, but to
learn how to construct programs. Right now, I don&amp;rsquo;t know how much of this will relate to
the idioms of each language (the structure of a Haskell is different in certain ways from
a Python program). But I do know that learning different idioms is good. In fact,
learning Haskell is one recommended way of getting better at Python (or even programming
in general).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep plugging away and finding bigger projects, whatever they
may be. Currently on my radar are a toy browser engine in Rust, some exploration of AGA
ratings, some graphing for a nonlinear dynamics class, and hopefully some fun small project
in Haskell. I won&amp;rsquo;t try to go too big; I know that I need to build lots of small projects
first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_3&#34;&gt;Job Search&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So does any of this have to do with a job search? After all, I&amp;rsquo;m not building my skills
in a pattern that necessarily makes it obvious to future employers that I&amp;rsquo;m getting
better. I&amp;rsquo;ve been told quite a few times that it&amp;rsquo;s important to have projects to show,
especially for somebody who is self taught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess I wanted to give myself something to aspire to. While web development in and of
itself isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily a boring job, I wanted to know a little better what it would
take to tackele interesting computational problems, whether in web development or in
another industry. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to just aim for patching together frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still glad I took the time to look around at the landscape and dig into some
fundamentals (I implemented binary trees in Haskell!). I know it will serve me well in
the future to have a broad outlook even at the beginning. I just have to keep going so I
can build skills that will actually be useful to employers, while also maintaining my
enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> New Journey</title>
      <link>http://waltherchen.com/post/NewJourney/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 14:04:09 EDT</pubDate>
      <author>Walther Chen</author>
      <guid>http://waltherchen.com/post/NewJourney/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting a new episode in my life! About one month ago, I committed myself
to learning programming and getting a job as a software developer. For at least
the next five years, I want to learn some new skills and explore a new
industry. After that, I&amp;rsquo;ll reassess and see where I want to go next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;Learning Programming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned Python through Think Python by Allen Downey, which I think
is an excellent book. I appreciated the thoughtful exercises, and the focus on
teaching only what&amp;rsquo;s useful in the moment while building towards a bigger
project. I find that too much information without implementation results in
shallow learning. Perhaps for other learners, there&amp;rsquo;s a different sweet spot,
but for me Think Python worked great. I&amp;rsquo;m even planning on working through his
book Think Complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some Python basics under my belt, I&amp;rsquo;m investigating some other projects.
The way my brain works, the computational aspect of CS doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem daunting,
but the organizational part does. For example, data structures in a void make sense, but
what&amp;rsquo;s the best way to organize them to do something useful? I guess this is
the software engineering side, and it looks quite open-ended and complex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current plans for Python projects are basic inventory management from CLI
and to investigate Flask. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve realized that I&amp;rsquo;m not very results
driven, I&amp;rsquo;m more of a process person. Of course, getting something to work is
satisfying, but I feel uncomfortable with magic and frameworks at the moment
because I don&amp;rsquo;t understand what&amp;rsquo;s going on. So as I continue to explore, those
projects may never get finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the theme of less magic, I&amp;rsquo;ve also been investigating Golang. I&amp;rsquo;ve finally
got it set up, and done some tutorials. I like the simplicity of the language,
and I want to use it to build a simple webserver first. Perhaps to serve sgf
files (Go game records).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a ton of other stuff I also find interesting: SICP,
Haskell, algorithms, data mining and analyis, numerical computing and
modelling. I&amp;rsquo;m all too capable of running off in many different directions. So
I&amp;rsquo;m going to shelve those for now and concentrate on Python and Golang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Finding a Job&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been networking with Williams alumni and they&amp;rsquo;ve been very kind and
helpful. I may have an internship set up for the near future, and I&amp;rsquo;ll also be
looking for other opportunities through more networking. I&amp;rsquo;ve found that my
default of responding to Craigslist ads has not worked especially well, maybe
because of my unconventional background. Although, I&amp;rsquo;m also planning on sending
some cold emails.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>